<sample>

  <title>DynarchLIB basics</title>

  <text>
    <p>
      DynarchLIB is a small, portable and efficient JavaScript
      framework providing the following:
    </p>
    <ul>

      <li><p>

        An <a href="sample://basic-objects.xml">unified coding
        style</a> suitable for writing small and elegant code, which
        leads to naturally small and fast applications.

      </p></li>

      <li><p>

        A collection of utility functions and useful extensions on top
        of standard JavaScript objects, which makes programming easier
        and more fun.

      </p></li>

      <li><p>

        A rich and extensible <a href="sample://widgets.xml">set of
        <em>widgets</em></a> (user interface controls) having an
        uniform (but customizable) look and feel and a sane API.

      </p></li>

      <li><p>

        A <a href="sample://basic-events.xml">coherent event
        system</a> — unifies DOM events with custom events and makes
        widgets behave as standard UI elements.

      </p></li>

      <li>
        <p>
          A server communication framework — provides an easy way to
          interoperate with a backend server via XML or <a
          href="sample://extensions-json.xml">JSON</a> RPC requests.
        </p>
        <p>
          Additionally, we provide 〈DlSocket〉, an object that you can
          use to create an arbitrary TCP/IP connection with the
          server.  This functionality requires Flash Player (it's a
          small SWF file of about 1K).
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          Strong 〈DlCryptAES|cryptographic functions〉 which you can
          use to encrypt/decrypt data when for any reasons you can't
          use SSL.
        </p>
      </li>

    </ul>

    <p>
      DynarchLIB is self-contained.  It is <em>not</em> based on
      Prototype, nor jQuery nor anything else.  I started DynarchLIB
      before I even knew about these libraries.  They are great tools,
      by the way, but DynarchLIB is just different in purpose; it
      represents a higher level, where you don't usually deal with DOM
      elements and DOM events, but with widgets having a custom event
      system instead; internally, DynarchLIB does the dirty work for
      you.
    </p>

    <h2>Browser support</h2>

    <p>
      DynarchLIB is designed with standards in mind.  In an ideal
      world, it will work on any browser.  (Well, in fact, in an ideal
      world, there would only be <em>one</em> browser and it would be
      <em>open-source</em>).  But since we don't live in an ideal
      world, here's the current status: <b>most things work in all
      modern browsers</b>, that is, Firefox, IE7, Safari, Konqueror
      and Opera (most things also work with IE6, but I definitely
      can't call it a <em>modern</em> browser).
    </p>

    <p>
      Even though DynarchLIB has been reasonably tested with all major
      browsers, you should remember that there's no silver bullet.  If
      you want to make sure that your application will support a
      particular browser, you do have to test.
    </p>

    <h3>Firefox and Internet Explorer 7</h3>

    <p>
      Though they are very different browsers, they are both very
      capable for rich AJAX applications.  Our main development
      platform is Firefox, but we extensively test what we do with IE7
      too.  DynarchLIB should work as documented in both Firefox and
      IE7.
    </p>

    <h3>Internet Explorer 6</h3>

    <p>
      This documentation might look weird in Internet Explorer 6, due
      to its lack of PNG support.  It's been more than 10 years since
      PNG has been standardised, therefore I decided to use it for the
      presentation pages.
    </p>

    <p>
      We are also using PNG images in order to draw dialog round
      corners and shadows.  Code based on DynarchLIB will still work
      in IE6, but won't look as good as in a modern browser (it
      automatically won't display round corners and shadows).
    </p>

    <p>
      These problems do not apply to IE7, which—eleven years after PNG
      has became a standard—finally introduces proper PNG support.
    </p>

    <h2>Note on Firebug</h2>

    <p>
      If you are using Firefox to test these samples and you have
      Firebug installed, we recommend you to disable it.  Otherwise
      certain operations might seem slow.  We don't know the reason
      for this but we suspect it's because Firebug must hook on a lot
      of browser events in order to provide all its great features;
      this in turn makes our scripts run slower.
    </p>

    <p>
      Firebug is a great debugger and profiler—a great tool for
      development—but when you want to test your application in
      real-world conditions always disable Firebug (preferably use a
      browser profile with no extensions).
    </p>

    <h2>What is this?</h2>

    <p>
      This application is an interactive documentation to DynarchLIB.
      It contains simple to advanced samples of how to use the toolkit
      efficiently.  You can run most of these samples directly through
      this application, and you can also edit them and test your
      changes.
    </p>

  </text>

</sample>
