<api file="layout.js" show="1">
  <object base="DlContainer" name="DlLayout">
    <constructor>
      <param default="true" name="fillParent" type="boolean">Passed to 〈DlContainer〉</param>
      <param default="0" name="outerSpace" type="Number">Outer space (padding) for this layout container</param>
      <doc>
        This class is useful to implement a fluid layout.  It's best
        suitable for vertical or horizontal layout, although you can
        use it to create more complex ones as well (i.e. combine
        vertical and horizontal containers in the same layout widget).
        See our <a href="sample://widgets-layout.xml">layout
        examples</a> for some sample code.

        In order to add widgets to a layout you need to call
        〈packWidget()|layout.packWidget(widget, args)〉.  Please check
        our samples and the 〈packWidget()〉 method for more
        information.
      </doc>
    </constructor>
    <static-methods>
      <method hash="5b8a48103b5779048e76c7d695bb326b" name="getArgs">
        <param name="widget" type="DlWidget">Queried widget</param>
        <return type="Hash">Layout args as passed to 〈packWidget()〉</return>
        <doc>
          Returns the layout options for the given widget.  These are
          the options that were passed to 〈packWidget()〉.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="3f79fd78af92e67c357b1da25e2f2a55" name="setFill">
        <param name="widget" type="DlWidget"></param>
        <param name="fill" type="Number|String">Fill argument</param>
        <doc>
          Modifies the <b>fill</b> argument for the given widget.  The
          widget must be 〈packWidget()|packed〉 in some layout.  This
          function will modify the fill option and will call
          〈doLayout()〉 in order to refresh the display.
        </doc>
      </method>
    </static-methods>
    <object-methods>
      <method hash="b18b327b28c99e62f03d2a62b48ed6ac" name="doLayout">
        <doc>
          Refresh the display (position and size child widgets
          according to their layout options).
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method XXX="Code has changed!" hash="4745a66523edf3243b735fe85895d5cf" name="packWidget">
        <param name="w" type="DlWidget">New child widget</param>
        <param name="args" type="Hash">Layout options</param>
        <doc>
          Adds a new widget to the current layout manager.  This is
          the method you'll use most frequently in a DlLayout object.

          First argument (<b>w</b>) is a widget that you want to add.
          In order for the layout to be able to do its job, widgets
          that you add to it must have a working implementation for
          their 〈DlWidget::setOuterSize()|setOuterSize()〉 method.

          The second argument (<b>args</b>) is an hash that can
          contain the following properties:

          <ul>

            <li><b>pos</b> (String) — can be "left" or "right"
            (horizontal stacking), "top" or "bottom" (vertical
            stacking) and specifies where do you want to stick the new
            widget.  <em>Required</em>.</li>

            <li><b>before</b> (Number) — specifies the number of
            pixels to leave blank <em>before</em> packing this
            widget.</li>

            <li><b>after</b> (Number) — number of pixels to leave
            blank <em>after</em> packing this widget</li>

            <li><b>min</b> (Number) — minimum size for this widget
            (can refer to width if it's stacked horizontally, or to
            the height if it's stacked vertically).</li>

            <li><b>max</b> (Number) — maximum width or height for this
            widget.</li>

            <li>
              <b>fill</b> (Number or String) — specifies a fill
              option for this widget.

              When this option is missing, the layout will use the
              current size of the given widget.  Note that this is
              sometimes dangerous—since the widget doesn't have a
              parent yet, its size is zero.  DlLayout will first add
              the widget then check its size, but in some cases this
              won't work either (for example when you pack another
              layout widget, since a DlLayout has initially the size
              zero and you have to set a size manually).

              If fill is a number, then the packed widget will
              occupy exactly that number of pixels in the layout (can
              refer to width or height depending on the <b>pos</b>
              argument).

              If fill is a string, it can be one of the
              following:

              <ul>
                <li>Percent (i.e. in the form "15%") — the widget will
                ocuppy that percent of the available space</li>

                <li>An asterisk ("*") — the widget will occupy
                <em>all</em> the available space.  Don't use this
                option for two wigets in the same layout.</li>
              </ul>
            </li>

          </ul>


        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="122662c0e3fce9d04386a21dd032a411" name="sizeToFit">
        <doc>
          XXX Dangerous, doesn't seem to work correctly

          This method is supposed to resize a layout to a minimum size
          which is big enough so that no child widgets are invisible
          or truncated.  But <em>don't rely on it for now</em>.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="7eb6428b725f29e8e18be0699d42f538" internal="1" name="__doLayout" undoc="1">
        <doc></doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="a0e44f7a1e50ab029ad0ae9b158221df" internal="1" name="_appendWidgetElement">
        <param name="w"></param>
        <param name="pos"></param>
        <doc></doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="36759034819d7d0c9a358167958b6609" internal="1" name="_removeWidgetElement">
        <param name="w"></param>
        <doc></doc>
      </method>
    </object-methods>
  </object>
</api>