<api file="rpc.js">
  <object base="DlEventProxy" name="DlRPC">
    <constructor>
      <param default="null" name="args" type="Hash">Arguments to pass to the server</param>
      <param default="null" name="callback" type="Function">Callback function that will be called when the request is completed (or when it times out)</param>
      <param default="null" name="data" type="String|Hash">Data to pass by POST</param>
      <param default="null" name="method" type="String">
        Request method ("GET" or "POST").  By default, this will be
        assumed "GET" if <b>data</b> is null, or "POST" if <b>data</b>
        is present.
      </param>
      <param default="null" name="timeout" type="Number">
        Maximum time allowed for the request (in milliseconds).  If
        the request doesn't complete after the specified timeout, it
        will be stopped, the "onTimeout" event will trigger and your
        callback will be called with <b>{ success:false, timeout: true
        }</b>.
      </param>
      <param default="null" name="url" type="String">URL for the request.</param>

      <doc>
        You can use this object to initiate a “remote procedure call”.
        This is a fancy name for a simple HTTP request.  Internally it
        uses the XMLHttpRequest object available in most browsers, or
        the ActiveX object for IE6.

        XMLHttpRequest was designed for sending pieces of XML data.
        This works via DynarchLIB as well, but we really recommend you
        to use 〈DlJSON|json〉—it reduces the complexity of your code a
        lot and it's faster for the browser to run.

        You initiate a call i.e. like this:

        <js>
          function myCallback(answer) {
            if (answer.success) {
              // use answer.text here to get text data, or
              // use answer.xml here to get a XMLDocument
              // (only if your server sent XML back)
            }
          };
          var rpc = new DlRPC({ url      : "http://server.com/rpchandler.cgi",
                                callback : myRpcCallback
                                data     : "Anything you want" });
          rpc.call(); // start
        </js>

        Because you pass <b>data</b> and no <b>method</b>, the above
        will automatically chose "POST".  The way you handle
        <b>data</b> on the server is completely up to you—you can
        retrieve the entire request content and do anything custom you
        want; it's not like you submit a form.  We found this to be
        the most flexible approach because we send JSON which is
        really easy to parse both on the server and client.

        You can pass both GET arguments and POST data as well:

        <js>
          new DlRPC({ url : "http://server.com/rpc-handler",
                      args : { foo: "foo",
                               bar: "bar" },
                      data : "Anything you want" }).call();
        </js>

        The above would actually call an URL like this:

        <pre>http://server.com/rpc-handler?foo=foo;bar=bar</pre>

        and will still send <b>data</b> in POST.  On the server-side
        you read <b>args</b> normally (just as if they were submitted
        by a form).

        If you want, you can send arguments in POST as well.  This
        will be as if you submit a form via POST, therefore you can
        access the arguments on the server-side via standard means.
        In this case, you cannot send additional <b>data</b> (but you
        can embed anything you want in arguments, therefore this won't
        be a problem):

        <js>
          new DlRPC({ url  : ...,
                      args : { foo  : "foo",
                               bar  : "bar",
                               data : "Anything you want" },
                      method : "POST" }).call();
        </js>

        Note that you need to explicitly specify the method here
        ("POST"), otherwise "GET" will be chosen by default.

        If you use JSON to communicate with the server, DlRPC will
        provide an useful shortcut: <b>data</b> can be a JavaScript
        object (Array or Hash), in which case it will be JSON-ized
        before its sent:

        <js>
          new DlRPC({ url : "http://server/json-handler",
                      data : { foo      : "foo",
                               bar      : "bar",
                               anything : [ "you", "want" ]
                             }
                    }).call();
        </js>

        On the server you would read the full request body and just
        de-JSONize to transform it into a native object for your
        programming language.

        In conclusion: you use this object to create a non-apparent
        request to the server.  It won't reload your page and you can
        attach a callback to be called when the request was finished.
        All requests are asynchronous—so if you expect an answer from
        the server you <em>need</em> to pass a callback.

        XXX One request per DlRPC object

        It is not safe for now to assume that one DlRPC object can
        handle multiple requests.  This means, you should only issue
        one 〈call()〉 request.  If you need to do another request to
        the server, be it with the same or different arguments, please
        instantiate a new DlRPC object.

        XXX Security

        It's important to know that browser security restrictions will
        forbid you to do XMLHttpRequest-s on other servers.  This
        means that the domain of the main document must be exactly the
        same as the domain where you'll do RPC requests.  If you need
        to do requests on different domains, the usual solution is to
        proxy the request through your own server.
      </doc>
    </constructor>
    <events>
      <event name="onStart">
        <param name="self" type="DlRPC">Request object</param>
        <doc>Triggered when the request starts.</doc>
      </event>
      <event name="onStop">
        <param name="self" type="DlRPC">Request object</param>
        <param name="args" type="Hash">Arguments from constructor</param>
        <param name="req" type="XMLHttpRequest">Low-level request object</param>
        <doc>
          Called when the request was completed.  Note that this event
          won't be called when the request times out.
        </doc>
      </event>
      <event name="onTimeout">
        <param name="self" type="DlRPC">Request object</param>
        <param name="req" type="XMLHttpRequest">Low-level request object</param>
        <doc>
          Triggered when the request times out.
        </doc>
      </event>
    </events>
    <static-methods></static-methods>
    <object-methods>
      <method XXX="Code has changed!" hash="63e9a0a2e5247c4da8aad6147dde1f40" name="call">
        <param name="newArgs" type="Hash">You can override here any arguments from constructor.  That's not very useful.</param>
        <doc>
          Call this method to start the request.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="b78ed49d4396eb2f9955b1f29a78a2a2" internal="1" name="_start">
        <param name="data"></param>
        <doc></doc>
      </method>
    </object-methods>
  </object>
</api>