<api file="socket.js" show="1">
  <object base="DlEventProxy" name="DlSocket">
    <constructor>
      <param default="null" name="host" type="String">
        Host name to connect to.  If this is <b>null</b> (default) it
        will be assumed its the domain of the document
        (document.domain).
      </param>
      <param default="null" name="port" type="String">
        Port to connect to.
      </param>
      <param default="false" name="json" type="boolean">
        Assume responses from server are JSON? (if <b>true</b>, it
        decodes incoming data automatically).
      </param>

      <doc>
        This is a general purpose object that allows you to connect to
        an arbitrary server via a TCP/IP connection.  It does not use
        the HTTP protocol which is actually a great advantage because
        it allows you to <em>stay connected</em> with the server
        (while HTTP is a request/response protocol).

        This functionality is not ordinarily exposed by browsers in
        JavaScript (and I will never understand why), so we have to
        use a plugin.  We chose to implement this via Flash, because
        it's widely available.  Therefore, please note that this
        object is only usable on browsers where Flash 8 (or newer) is
        installed.  Call
        〈DlFlashUtils::isSupported()|DlFlashUtils().isSupported()〉 to
        check if the browser “speaks” the required version of Flash.

        *** Pros and Cons for using this object

        <b>Advantages:</b> it allows you to keep a persistent
        connection with the server.  This means that you can do
        authentication only once and then send data between browser
        and server at will.  The server can chose to send data that
        the client didn't previously request.  This is useful when
        implementing real-time actions such as a game or a chat.
        Browser instantly receives data from server when it is
        available.  You don't need to poll the server or implement
        “hanging requests” in order to get server notifications—the
        server knows all clients and will send data whenever it needs.

        <b>Disadvantages:</b> it requires Flash Player 8.0 or newer.
        It loads a (very small—around 1K) SWF file (you need to call
        〈DlFlashUtils::init()|DlFlashUtils().init()〉).  It doesn't
        work over SSL since this is not supported by Flash's XMLSocket
        (but see our 〈DlCryptAES〉 object which enables you to encrypt
        communication).  It requires a custom server (I'm not sure it
        can work with Apache, Tomcat, or other HTTP servers, since
        it's not about HTTP).  See below for some hints.

        *** Usage

        Here is an example of how to use this object:

        <js>
          var socket = new DlSocket({ host: document.domain,
                                      port: 12345 });
          socket.addEventListener("onConnect", function(success) {
              if (success) {
                  // successful connection, you can begin using the socket here
              } else {
                  alert("Could not connect to server");
              }
          });

          socket.addEventListener("onData", function(data) {
              alert("Got data from server: " + data);
          });

          socket.connect();

          // note that you can call the following only after
          // you have a successful connection
          // ("onConnect" event triggered with success = true)

          // send data to server
          socket.send("Foo bar baz");

          // send object to server (will be JSON-ized)
          socket.sendJSON({ foo: "foo", bar: "bar" });

          // reconnect after a downtime:
          socket.reconnect(); // will trigger "onConnect"

          // disconnect from server:
          socket.disconnect();

          // completely destroy the socket:
          socket.destroy(); // implies disconnect() first
        </js>

        *** Notes

        <b>Binary data.</b> DlSocket internally uses an XMLSocket
        Flash object.  One limitation of it is that the null ("\0")
        character marks the end of data.  Therefore you must be
        careful when you send binary data—it will actually send upto
        the first zero byte.  On the server side, you must send a zero
        byte after each reply, in order for the browser to receive any
        data.

        Since it isn't usual to generate truly binary data in
        JavaScript, this shouldn't be a serious limitation.  But you
        need to know it.

        <b>Fully asynchronous.</b> This kind of client-server
        communication is completely asynchronous.  It is <em>not</em>
        a request/response protocol.

        When you use 〈send()〉 or 〈sendJSON()〉 you need to be careful
        that these functions send the data but don't return anything,
        so don't expect an immediate reply from the server.  They give
        back control to the calling program immediately—while the
        server might still process the data.

        If the server replies, you will get the answer via the
        "onData" event.

        It's completely up to you to design a communication protocol
        suitable for your application.

        *** Hints for the server-side

        This kind of communication requires some network programming
        skills for the server-side.  You will need to implement your
        own server that binds to a port and listens for incoming
        connections.  For an incoming connection it should
        authenticate the client and probably spawn a new thread, or
        process, to handle that connection.  All this isn't very
        complicated, but it's beyond ordinary “web development”
        knowledge.

      </doc>
    </constructor>
    <events>
      <event name="onConnect">
        <param name="success" type="boolean">Successful connection?</param>
        <doc>
          Triggered when a socket is successfully connected (in which
          case <b>success</b> will be true) or when connection failed
          (<b>success</b> is false).  Only after this event was
          triggered with <b>success = true</b> you can do other calls
          on the socket.
        </doc>
      </event>
      <event name="onRelease">
        <param name="reason" type="Number">Reason why this socket was closed</param>
        <doc>
          Triggered when the socket was “released”.  This can happen
          when the connection is lost because of network outage or
          server shutdown (reason == 0), or when you called
          〈disconnect()〉 (reason == 1) or when you called 〈destroy()〉
          (reason == 2).

          Note that after this event is triggered you cannot use the
          socket until you 〈reconnect()〉 or 〈connect()〉 it again.
        </doc>
      </event>
      <event name="onData">
        <param name="data">Incoming data from server</param>
        <doc>
          Triggered when the server has sent data for us.  The
          <b>data</b> will usually be a String, but it can be an Hash
          as well if you passed <b>json: true</b> in constructor.
        </doc>
      </event>
    </events>
    <static-methods></static-methods>
    <object-methods>
      <method hash="3c72082ff50bf6782090f85a4f662e70" name="connect">
        <doc>
          Call this method to initiate a connection.  It will trigger
          the "onConnect" event both on a successful connection or
          when there's some error.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="f93b1bf4a667eb938b740bf0be7b0718" name="disconnect">
        <doc>
          Disconnect the socket.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="9250f32f8218f632d925504913998e52" name="reconnect">
        <doc>
          Reconnect a disconnected socket.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="bfece44c4c4fc1d4c44cda10010f7c26" name="send">
        <param name="data" type="String">Data to send to server</param>
        <doc>
          Send the given data to the server-side.  Note that this
          method is asynchronous and doesn't return anything.  Add
          your handler to the "onData" event in order to process
          incoming data from server.
        </doc>
      </method>
      <method hash="aaa683ed4ba46c11ba52fa35e13e2c03" name="sendJSON">
        <param name="data">Data to send to server</param>
        <doc>
          This function is just like 〈send()〉 but it will
          〈DlJSON.encode()|JSON-encode〉 the data before sending it.
        </doc>
      </method>
    </object-methods>
  </object>
</api>