<api file="stylesheet.js" show="1">
  <object base="DlEventProxy" name="DlStyleSheet">

    <constructor>
      Object to create and manipulate an inline stylesheet.  You can
      use this object to dynamically insert random CSS rules that
      apply to all document.

      For example, if I wanted to <em>dynamically</em> decide that all
      DIV-s with class “foo-style” should have red text, we can do the
      following (see the text below before you execute the sample):

      <js canrun="1">
        var style = new DlStyleSheet();
        style.insertRule(".foo-style", { color: "red", padding: "1em" });
        print("Now close the dialog and watch the Foo Text");
      </js>

      <div class="foo-style">
        Some <b>Foo Text</b> Here.
      </div>

      Note that these are global styles.  The above defined style will
      apply, from now on, to all elements in the document that have
      the "foo-style" class name.

      If you save the value returned by 〈insertRule()〉, you can
      〈deleteRule()|remove〉 the rule or 〈modifyRule()|modify〉 it
      later.
    </constructor>

    <static-methods></static-methods>

    <object-methods>

      <method hash="a06585d096254703907e0ae43bbd1bdb" name="deleteRule">
        <param name="rule">CSS rule to remove</param>
        <doc>
          If you want to completely remove a certain rule, call this
          function and pass it the value returned by 〈insertRule()〉.
        </doc>
      </method>

      <method hash="32a232ebbf7c354f868e5769f7eb30b3" name="disabled">
        <param default="null" name="dis" optional="1" type="boolean">Disable this style?</param>
        <doc>
          Disable or enable this stylesheet, if <b>dis</b> is passed.
          If <b>dis</b> is null, simply return <b>true</b> if the
          stylesheet is currently disabled, or false otherwise.
        </doc>
      </method>

      <method hash="c5bbc0c92cdc2f52404c5e1ee655c040" name="getRules">
        <doc>
          Returns an array with all rules in this stylesheet.  Note
          that these are actually objects of type <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/DOM-Level-2-Style/css.html#CSS-CSSStyleRule" target="_blank">CSSStyleRule</a> (as defined by W3C DOM CSS
          specification), except for IE where they are proprietary.

          You shouldn't find much use for this method.
        </doc>
      </method>

      <method hash="a2d056d56396182ea1c1c59cc3d457c8" name="insertRule">
        <param name="sel" type="String">CSS Selector</param>
        <param name="style" type="String|Hash">CSS rule definition</param>
        <param default="null" name="index" optional="1" type="Number">position where to insert this rule in the current stylesheet</param>
        <return>CSS rule (index or object! see below)</return>
        <doc>
          If <b>index</b> is null (default) the rule will be appended
          (thus, at the end).

          This function inserts a new rule into the current
          stylesheet.  The selector is a standard CSS selector, i.e.:

          <ul>
            <li> .someClassName </li>
            <li> h1 </li>
            <li> #someID </li>
            <li> .someClassName, .otherClassName </li>
          </ul>

          etc.  Any standard CSS selectors should be supported.  Even
          in IE.

          The <b>style</b> is either a string specifying the CSS text,
          or an object (which serves the same purpose):

          <ul>
            <li> "color: red"</li>
            <li> { color: "red" }</li>
            <li> "color red; background-color: yellow" </li>
            <li> { color: "red", "background-color" : "yellow" } </li>
          </ul>

          The return value is either an object or an index, depending
          on the browser and the selector form.  IE does not support
          multiple selectors (separated by commas) so we had to work
          around this, but in this case we don't return a CSS rule
          object but an internal ID.

          Either way, you should not worry about the return value—just
          save it if you intend to call later 〈deleteRule()〉 or
          〈modifyRule()〉.
        </doc>
      </method>

      <method hash="cb94160971ff9bc5542eaa5a16039388" name="modifyRule">
        <param name="rule">CSS rule as returned by 〈insertRule()〉</param>
        <param name="changes" type="Hash">What to change?</param>
        <doc>
          Modify a rule previously inserted with 〈insertRule()〉.
          <b>rule</b> is whatever was returned by 〈insertRule()〉 and
          <b>changes</b> is a hash, i.e.:

          <js>
            style.modifyRule(rule, { "background-color" : "red",
                                     "color"            : "white" });
          </js>
        </doc>
      </method>

      <method hash="46da4630bef8ac0f9fcf6b23586ee59c" name="refresh">
        <doc>
          In rare situations (that is, never) you will want to try
          this method to refresh the page after you changed the
          stylesheet.  It does <em>not</em> reload the page, it just
          forces a style refresh by calling
          〈disabled()|disabled(false)〉 and then disabled(true). (an
          old hack that used to be needed for Gecko).
        </doc>
      </method>

      <method hash="bd203fd4e6bf2db71a4ca797db2ac456" internal="1" name="_init">
        <doc></doc>
      </method>

    </object-methods>
  </object>
</api>